<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Erika&#39;s Blog</title>
    <description>AWS-focused tutorials for services that are tough to learn with existing resources. Created by Erika Burdon. Live examples hosted at erikaburdon.ca.</description>
    <link>http://eburdon.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://eburdon.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 08:11:57 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 08:11:57 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Plaintext Login Details</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I registered for a new online community for ladies in technology. Part of the whole “get-out-there” goal. I went through the standard process of signing up with my email, using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lastpass.com/&quot;&gt;LastPass&lt;/a&gt; to generate a new password and save the entry in my vault, so on and so forth. I was pretty alarmed when I received an email half a minute later with all my login details… &lt;em&gt;including the password in plaintext&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&quot;Congratulations on entering the tech community!

The login information for your account is: 
Email: email@email
Password: password

...&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are your thoughts on this? I asked around - it seems like this used to be standard practice. It’s old, but still fine to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I explored the community a bit more and it was clear that the website doesn’t handle any personal information about it’s users. There’s no profile or chat section. The website is mostly links to local events and job postings. It’s clear this isn’t a high-security venture and strong password protection may not be necessary. That said, I truly think all services should take every step they can to help users protect and increase their online security. What if I wasn’t using a password generator, and my unique password was actually already in use on another platform? Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an alternative, look at how Slack handles new users. When registering for a new channel, you receive a little email like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&quot;Your Slack Account Information

Hi Erika, 

Welcome to Slack! You&#39;ve joined the team teamName. In case it&#39;s handy,
here&#39;s a copy of your account details:

Team Name: teamName
Team Domain: http://teamURL
Sign-in Email Address: email@email

...&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This serves the same purpose with all the info you need without the password. I like how it doesn’t assume my email inbox is absolutely secure while still providing useful information I can archive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reached out to the new community’s help desk and was really happy with the response. The company they hired said it’s standard to include the password, but the community agreed that it should be removed for the extra security and so it will be phased out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-do-you-think-of-emailing-users-their-account-information-on-sign-up-still-required-should-passwords-be-included&quot;&gt;What do you think of emailing users their account information on sign-up? Still required? Should passwords be included?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As always, image sourced from Unsplash. By &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/MZnuRv1ZASk&quot;&gt;Rob Sarmiento&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://eburdon.github.io/2017/01/17/on-plaintext-login/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://eburdon.github.io/2017/01/17/on-plaintext-login/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Security</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Updates and Goals</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Well. That didn’t kick off too fabulously. In hindsight, it was probably a bad idea trying to start a development blog just as the holidays were ramping up, and work was closing down for the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start the second week of 2017 with a quick review of my project goals for the next year. The overarching one is to &lt;strong&gt;git gud.&lt;/strong&gt; I know I have knowledge gaps in Computer Science and Software Engineering. Some should probably be fundamental at this point (binary trees, for example). I also don’t deeply understand the caveats of developing in one browser over another (Chrome vs Edge), or what makes one language more powerful than another. I gotta fill these in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.giphy.com/rmRDNnH9rW3wQ.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;projects&quot;&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned way back when, I’d like to update this blog on a regular basis. That’s still a goal. I suspect what stopped me over the holiday months was the idea that every post had to be this monolithic, complete thing with deep substance. Like a good hackathon project, I need to scale back the scope of my ideas and get stuff written! Adding to that, I’d like to develop a stronger stance on some engineering topics. I suspect I’m being too ‘wishy-washy’ about topics that seem to fire passionate debates online. This may come from those nusiance knowledge gaps! I’ll do this by digging into those debates and continuing with my umbrella review of architectures, design, code smells, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my &lt;em&gt;tangible&lt;/em&gt; goals is to finish 1 / 2 current side projects: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/eburdon/erikaburdonAPI&quot;&gt;ClusterCooking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. I’m redoing my site’s backend to support this (Pull request coming soon). It’s an API written in Scala so I might learn some functional programming, with the intent of build an Android App and web interface to interact with it. It’ll help you plan your meals for the week. So far, I’ve got the basic CRUD actions complete for two of the data models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClusterCooking has already been the source of several draft posts, so keep an eye out for those. Once I get V0.01 online and the code in the repo, I’ll open them up for comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My other side project is a pseudo data-mining project of Facebook personal data anyone can download from their settings. Written in GO, this project started in my distributed systems course as an example of parallelizing data. I hope to implement at least one algorithm iterating over the data to provdide useful information, and to host the tool on &lt;a href=&quot;http://erikaburdon.ca&quot;&gt;erikaburdon.ca&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t think I’ll get that one done this year, but a girl can dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shoutouts&quot;&gt;Shoutouts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/f3rOCKaFcspyw/source.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close, I’d like to give a quick shoutout to some resources I found over the holidays that have helped me out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;devto&quot;&gt;Dev.to&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curated by the folks behind &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thepracticaldev&quot;&gt;@ThePracticalDev&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/&quot;&gt;DEV.to&lt;/a&gt; is a space for any developer to “submit stories, tutorials, or anything worth discussing.” So far, it’s been a great community to hop into and chat with. With tons of social and technical posts, it was great reading when winding down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;alvin-alexander&quot;&gt;Alvin Alexander&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to say thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://alvinalexander.com/&quot;&gt;Alvin Alexander&lt;/a&gt; and all his Scala tutorials! Definitely helped me resolve some issues I’ve had with ClusterCooking over the past month. I think I’ve used his site more than StackOverflow lately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tech-ladies&quot;&gt;Tech Ladies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I signed up for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hiretechladies.com/&quot;&gt;Tech Ladies&lt;/a&gt;, a rather self-explanitory online community! They’ve got a private Facebook group which has already proven to be a great outreach resource. I’ve already had two positive experiences with them, one being their help desk addressing and updating their password policy based on a concern of mine. I’m curious what other people think about the exchange, so expect a post about that soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ben-halpern&quot;&gt;Ben Halpern&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just really love his website. &lt;a href=&quot;http://benhalpern.com/&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-your-project-goals--shoutouts-to-kick-off-2017&quot;&gt;What are your project goals &amp;amp; shoutouts to kick off 2017?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tweet me at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/OneEaredMusic&quot;&gt;@OneEaredMusic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://eburdon.github.io/2017/01/09/updates-and-goals/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://eburdon.github.io/2017/01/09/updates-and-goals/</guid>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ACCESS DENIED: Reset MySQL root user password</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an aggregation of various Stack Overflow posts, user tutorials, and official docs that helped me figure out how to reset my local MySQL root password.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to an early engineering assignment, my initial database setup got &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; screwed up. Being the middle of a semester, I didn’t have the time to fix it. Now, a couple of updates later, I had to face the beast and get it working. For future reference for myself and for anyone else stuck, this is a brief post on the steps I took that worked for my system. All the tutorials I found during my fix-it session were either incomplete or not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stats&quot;&gt;Stats&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OS: Ubuntu 16.04.1 LTS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MySQL: 5.7.15&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sit-rep&quot;&gt;Sit-rep&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve installed, and re-installed, and tried to repair an old MySQL installation. Entering&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mysql -u root -p&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;followed by your password, returns an&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Access denied for user &#39;root&#39;@&#39;localhost&#39; &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;error, even though you’re sure it’s the right login. You’ve also already tried the official documentation on &lt;a href=&quot;http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.7/en/resetting-permissions.html&quot;&gt;How to reset the root password&lt;/a&gt;, which failed. Maybe you even tried to repackage the deb file with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo dpkg-reconfigure mysql-server-5.7&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which failed. Have no fear - where there’s a terminal, there’s a way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1&quot;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shut down Mysql. Try&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo service mysql stop&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo /etc/init.d/mysql stop&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or looking up the PID and killing it. Make sure it’s stopped via:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;service mysql status&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2&quot;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start MySQL in safe mode without a password:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mysqld_safe --skip-grant-tables &amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caution: this is insecure! I had no data in any of my tables, which meant I wasn’t worried about malicious reads. The ‘skip’ option enables anyone to connect without a password with full privileges. If you have &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; concerns about your tables, you should also diable any remote access with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--skip-networking&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3&quot;&gt;Step 3&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a new terminal, connect to MySQL server with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mysql&lt;/code&gt; client. No password is neccessary. Execute the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;use mysql;&lt;/code&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;UPDATE user SET authentication_string=PASSWORD(&quot;securepassword&quot;) where User=&#39;root&#39;;&lt;/code&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;UPDATE user SET plugin=&quot;mysql_native_password&quot;;&lt;/code&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;FLUSH PRIVILEGES;&lt;/code&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;quit;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brief explanation: The second line is obviously where you set your password. One difference between MySQL 5.6 or older, and the latest 5.7+ is the column name switch from &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PASSWORD&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;AUTHENTICATION_STRING.&lt;/code&gt; Older tutorials obviously use the former.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you miss the third ‘set plugin’ statement, you’ll successfully update your password but still won’t be able to connect to your server. My system, for example, had the plugin value set to ‘auth socket.’ Even with the right login details, my server threw errors about my missing socket, and I needed to shut down, restart in safe mode, and switch both values again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the ‘flush privileges’ command reloads the server’s in-memory copy of the grant tables. Modifying the user table with UPDATE doesn’t load the changes into the tables immediately, unlike the higher-level GRANT or SET commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-4&quot;&gt;Step 4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stop your safe mysqld, and start the mysql server normally. You should be able to connect with your new password via&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mysql -u root -p&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy your new database access!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MySQL Reference Manual: &lt;a href=&quot;http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.7/en/resetting-permissions.html&quot;&gt;How to reset the root password&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stack Overflow: &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/30692812/mysql-user-db-does-not-have-password-columns-installing-mysql-on-osx&quot;&gt;MySQL User DB does not have password columns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stack Overflow: &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/11091414/how-to-stop-mysqld&quot;&gt;How to stop mysqld&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stack Overflow: &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/37879448/mysql-fails-on-mysql-error-1524-hy000-plugin-auth-socket-is-not-loaded&quot;&gt;MySQL Fails on: mysql “ERROR 1524 (HY000)”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dbahire.com/stop-using-flush-privileges/&quot;&gt;Stop Using Flush Privileges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://eburdon.github.io/2016/09/10/mysql-root-password/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://eburdon.github.io/2016/09/10/mysql-root-password/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Databases</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello, what&#39;s this?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks for checking in! You’ve reached yet another technical blog. This one is created and maintained by Erika Burdon, wannabe Software Engineer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve created this space in an effort to generate some tutorials on things that are difficult, and/or mildly confusing to learn with current resources. Things such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/emr/&quot;&gt;Amazon Web Service’s Elastic Map Reduce&lt;/a&gt;. I used this service in a recent project, and it was bit of a doozy to master. A few friends of mine had a deep interest in using it themselves, but didn’t have time to climb the learning curve. There may also be the occassional motivational posts on engineering and skill development. Content will come as I learn them in my own projects, all of which are hosted live on my website &lt;a href=&quot;http://erikaburdon.ca&quot;&gt;erikaburdon.ca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any suggestions for blog posts, questions, or just feel like saying hi, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:erikaeburdon@gmail.com&quot;&gt;feel free to reach out&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-are-you&quot;&gt;Who are you?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have guessed it already, but my name is Erika Burdon. I’ll be graduating from the University of Victoria in Spring 2017 with a bachelor’s in Software Engineering. I’ve got a problem with wanting to learn everything but no time to do it. I’m most interested in program architectures, especially with how third party libraries are integrated into systems.  I’m also a whiz at cooking and love to wakeboard. I’m deeply interested in music, puns, and living on the west coast. Also, cats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://erikaburdon.ca&quot;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;~&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/eburdon&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;~&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/eburdon&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;~&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/OneEaredMusic&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;upcoming-content&quot;&gt;Upcoming content&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be honest. We’re all very busy people and life sometimes takes over with busy-ness. There’s overtime at work, and holidays coming up. Other times, you just don’t want to do anything at all. That said, there’s little worse than a dead blog. I hope to get at least 1 new post every 2 months. More likely, it’ll be 1 post per quarter, but a girl can dream. Check back when you can, or send me an email to let me know you’d like a notification when something new is up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[AWS] &lt;br /&gt;
 * Your first AWS EMR project &lt;br /&gt;
 * Creating an microservice using AWS Lambda &lt;br /&gt;
 * Spot vs Reserved Instances &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[SKILL DEVELOPMENT] &lt;br /&gt;
* Goodbye to the Comfort Zone &lt;br /&gt;
* Long-term projects (Student Version) &lt;br /&gt;
* Long-term projects (Professor Version) &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[GENERAL] &lt;br /&gt; 
* Mega-link thread of Resources &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thanks-for-checking-in&quot;&gt;Thanks for checking in!&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://eburdon.github.io/2016/09/08/hello/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://eburdon.github.io/2016/09/08/hello/</guid>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
